<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://emilyedited.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://emilyedited.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-06-13T22:44:33+01:00</updated><id>https://emilyedited.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Emily Edited</title><subtitle>Science and Psychology. </subtitle><author><name>Emily Towner</name><email>hello@emilytowner.com</email></author><entry><title type="html">Psychology 101 (Part 1) - Your Mind: The Most Complex Thing in the Universe</title><link href="https://emilyedited.com/psychology/2025/06/05/mind-most-complex.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Psychology 101 (Part 1) - Your Mind: The Most Complex Thing in the Universe" /><published>2025-06-05T11:30:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-06-05T11:30:00+01:00</updated><id>https://emilyedited.com/psychology/2025/06/05/mind-most-complex</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://emilyedited.com/psychology/2025/06/05/mind-most-complex.html"><![CDATA[<p>Here’s something that’ll blow your mind: according to astronomer Owen Gingerich, while outer space is mind-bogglingly vast, the <em>human brain</em> is actually the most complex physical object we know of in the entire cosmos. Think about that for a second. Forget black holes and distant galaxies—the most intricate thing we’ve discovered is sitting right between your ears.</p>

<h2 id="the-science-of-being-human">The Science of Being Human</h2>

<p>Psychology isn’t just therapy sessions or common sense dressed up in fancy language. At its core, it’s the science of behavior and mental processes—everything from why you can remember song lyrics from high school but forget where you put your keys, to how we form relationships and make decisions. Psychology as a science (and more recently neuroscience) has spent over a century figuring out how our minds (and brains) work. The complexity is both amazing and, well, a bit problematic. Because our incredibly sophisticated brains have some built-in quirks that can lead us astray.</p>

<p>Sometimes after something happens—let’s say your favorite sports team loses a crucial match—suddenly it feels like you “totally saw it coming”? Or how about when you’re absolutely certain you know something, only to discover you were completely wrong? Yeah, that’s not just you being weird. There’s actually fascinating psychology behind why this happens, and understanding it might just change how you look at the world.</p>

<p>What makes psychology particularly fascinating is how it challenges our intuitions. You know those contradictory sayings we all love? “Absence makes the heart grow fonder” versus “Out of sight, out of mind.” They can’t both be universally true, right? This is where scientific thinking comes in—rather than just accepting what feels right, psychology demands evidence.</p>

<h2 id="three-mental-traps-we-all-fall-into">Three Mental Traps We All Fall Into</h2>

<p>The research reveals three major ways our brains consistently “trick” us, and honestly, once you know about them, you’ll start seeing them everywhere.</p>

<h3 id="1-the-i-knew-it-all-along-effect">1. The “I Knew It All Along” Effect</h3>

<p>Picture this: you’re watching the news about some major political event or economic shift, and as the story unfolds, you think, “Well, of course that happened. It was so obvious.” This is <strong>hindsight bias</strong>, and it’s incredibly powerful.</p>

<p>Here’s the thing—when researchers tell people about an outcome and ask them to explain why it makes sense, they can do so brilliantly. But show them the same information beforehand and ask them to predict what will happen? Suddenly it’s not so obvious anymore.</p>

<p>This bias makes us think we’re much better at predicting the future than we actually are. It’s like having a superpower that only works backwards. The problem is, this overconfidence in our predictive abilities can lead us to make poor decisions going forward.</p>

<h3 id="2-the-confidence-trap">2. The Confidence Trap</h3>

<p>We’re consistently more confident than we are correct. Think about those word puzzles where you rearrange letters—like turning “OCHSA” into “CHAOS.” Once you know the answer, it feels like you would have gotten it immediately. But hand someone a new puzzle they haven’t seen before, and suddenly it takes much longer.</p>

<p>This overconfidence isn’t limited to word games. Research by Philip Tetlock showed that experts making confident predictions about world events were wrong more often than right. History is littered with hilariously overconfident predictions—like Wilbur Wright saying humans wouldn’t fly for a thousand years (in 1901, just before his brother proved him spectacularly wrong).</p>

<h3 id="3-seeing-patterns-in-randomness">3. Seeing Patterns in Randomness</h3>

<p>Our brains are pattern-detection machines, which is usually helpful. But sometimes we see meaningful patterns where none exist. We spot faces in clouds, think basketball players have “hot hands” when it’s just random variation, or believe we’ve cracked some cosmic code when we win the lottery twice.</p>

<p>The reality? Random sequences often don’t look random to us. With a large enough sample size, seemingly impossible coincidences become statistically inevitable. If something has a one-in-a-billion chance of happening to any person on any given day, it’ll still happen to about seven people worldwide <em>every single day</em>.</p>

<h2 id="why-this-matters-in-our-post-truth-world">Why This Matters in Our “Post-Truth” World</h2>

<p>These mental quirks make us vulnerable to misinformation. Consider this: many Americans believe crime rates are rising when they’ve actually fallen dramatically over decades. Or think about how anecdotes about vaccine side effects feel more compelling than comprehensive data showing dramatically lower death rates among vaccinated populations.</p>

<p>We fall for this stuff because of <strong>confirmation bias</strong> (seeking information that confirms what we already believe), <strong>emotional reasoning</strong> (if it feels true, it must be true), and simple <strong>repetition</strong> (hearing something multiple times makes it feel familiar and therefore credible).</p>

<h2 id="fighting-back-with-scientific-thinking">Fighting Back with Scientific Thinking</h2>

<p>So how do we combat these built-in biases? The answer lies in adopting what psychologists call a “scientific attitude”—a combination of curiosity, skepticism, and humility.</p>

<p><strong>Curiosity</strong> means staying genuinely interested in understanding how things really work, not just confirming what you already think.</p>

<p><strong>Skepticism</strong> doesn’t mean being cynical about everything, but rather demanding evidence. Remember James Randi, a Canadian-American stage magician, author, and scientific skeptic who extensively challenged paranormal and pseudoscientific claims, tested someone who claimed they could see auras? His simple challenge: “Can you see my aura if I stand behind this wall?” When they refused the test, that told the whole story.</p>

<p><strong>Humility</strong> might be the most important piece. It’s acknowledging that we all make mistakes and being willing to change our minds when evidence points in a different direction. As they say in psychology labs: “The rat is always right”—if your hypothesis doesn’t match the data, your idea might be wrong.</p>

<h2 id="putting-this-into-practice">Putting This Into Practice</h2>

<p>Here’s what you can do with this knowledge:</p>

<p><strong>Slow down your thinking.</strong></p>

<p>When you feel certain about something, especially if it confirms what you already believe, pause and ask: “What evidence am I basing this on? Could I be wrong?”</p>

<p><strong>Seek out disconfirming evidence.</strong></p>

<p>Actively look for information that challenges your views. It’s uncomfortable, but it’s how you grow.</p>

<p><strong>Remember the Royal Society motto: “Take nobody’s word for it.”</strong></p>

<p>Test ideas when you can, and be willing to live with uncertainty when you can’t.</p>

<p>The goal isn’t to become paralyzed by doubt—it’s to become more accurate in your thinking. Understanding these mental quirks doesn’t make you immune to them (I still fall for them all the time), but it does give you a fighting chance.</p>

<p>Your brain is indeed the most complex thing in the known universe. The least we can do is try to understand how it works—and where it might be leading us astray. Because once you start thinking like a scientist about your own thinking (so meta), you’ll never look at the world quite the same way again.</p>

<p><em>What’s one belief you hold strongly that you’ve never really questioned? What would it take to change your mind about it?</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Emily Towner</name><email>hello@emilytowner.com</email></author><category term="psychology" /><category term="psychology" /><category term="cognitive bias" /><category term="hindsight bias" /><category term="overconfidence" /><category term="scientific thinking" /><category term="critical thinking" /><category term="misinformation" /><category term="decision making" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Here’s something that’ll blow your mind: according to astronomer Owen Gingerich, while outer space is mind-bogglingly vast, the human brain is actually the most complex physical object we know of in the entire cosmos. Think about that for a second. Forget black holes and distant galaxies—the most intricate thing we’ve discovered is sitting right between your ears.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://emilyedited.com/assets/images/posts/2025/06/05/mind-most-complex.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://emilyedited.com/assets/images/posts/2025/06/05/mind-most-complex.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Fellowship Game: Insider Advice from Cambridge Researchers Who’ve Won (and Lost)</title><link href="https://emilyedited.com/academia/postdoctoral/2025/06/04/fellowship-game-insider.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Fellowship Game: Insider Advice from Cambridge Researchers Who’ve Won (and Lost)" /><published>2025-06-04T11:30:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-06-04T11:30:00+01:00</updated><id>https://emilyedited.com/academia/postdoctoral/2025/06/04/fellowship-game-insider</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://emilyedited.com/academia/postdoctoral/2025/06/04/fellowship-game-insider.html"><![CDATA[<p>Postdoctoral fellowships receive a vast number of applications for a very limited number of positions. This sobering reality captures the harsh truth about academic fellowships. However, at the same time, a really good predictor of fellowship success comes down to how many times you’ve applied and how persistent you are.</p>

<p>These insights emerged from a recent fellowship workshop at the University of Cambridge, where three accomplished researchers—Sarah-Jayne Blakemore, Professor of Psychology and Cognitive Neuroscience; Camilla Nord, head of the Mental Health Neuroscience programme at the MRC Cognition and Brain Sciences Unit; and Sara de Felice, a social neuroscientist and Marie Skłodowska-Curie Fellow—shared hard-won wisdom on navigating the competitive landscape of research fellowships. Their advice offers so much more than just standard application tips; it unveils the strategic thinking and emotional resilience that  empower you to thrive in modern academia.</p>

<h2 id="the-strategic-question-fellowship-or-not">The Strategic Question: Fellowship or Not?</h2>
<p>Before diving into application strategies, the speakers tackled a fundamental question that many early-career researchers grapple with: Should you even pursue a fellowship?</p>

<p><strong>Fellowships are not for everyone</strong>, and that is perfectly acceptable. As Sarah-Jayne Blakemore emphasized, “Choosing not to go down the fellowship route is absolutely fine.”</p>

<p>The key is understanding what fellowships actually offer:</p>

<h3 id="advantages-of-fellowships">Advantages of fellowships</h3>
<ul>
  <li>Intellectual freedom to pursue your own research questions</li>
  <li>Prestige and recognition that can accelerate career advancement</li>
  <li>Independence and autonomy in directing your work</li>
  <li>Freedom to take risks and shift into new fields</li>
  <li>Ability to build collaborations on your own terms</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="disadvantages-of-fellowships">Disadvantages of fellowships:</h3>
<ul>
  <li>Extremely time-consuming application process</li>
  <li>Very low success rates create high opportunity costs</li>
  <li>Some fellowships come with minimal research expenses</li>
  <li>The pressure of being solely responsible for your research direction</li>
</ul>

<p>Alternative paths, such as postdoctoral positions on other people’s grants, offer their own benefits: faster application processes, guaranteed research funding, mentorship from established principal investigators (PIs), and the ability to focus entirely on research rather than grant management.</p>

<h2 id="the-independence-imperative">The Independence Imperative</h2>
<p>One of the key takeaways from the workshop was this: <em>“Grant panels want to see you as independent from your PhD supervisor.”</em></p>

<p>This independence requirement shapes every aspect of successful fellowship applications. Reviewers are specifically looking for evidence that you can function as an independent researcher, which means:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Publications without your PhD supervisor as a co-author</li>
  <li>Collaborations outside your PhD lab
    <ul>
      <li>Even during your PhD, seek opportunities to work with other groups</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Research questions that diverge from your thesis
    <ul>
      <li>Show you can think beyond your doctoral training</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h3 id="new-methodological-skills">New methodological skills</h3>
<p>Demonstrate you’re expanding your toolkit. One speaker shared that they completely shifted fields through their fellowship, something only possible because the fellowship provided the independence and intellectual freedom to take that risk.</p>

<h2 id="strategic-timing-and-planning">Strategic Timing and Planning</h2>
<p>Consider this timeline example: if you want funding to start in March 2027, you should start thinking seriously about applications in September 2025.</p>

<p>This 18-month lead time accounts for:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Research and networking phase (3-6 months):
    <ul>
      <li>Identifying potential mentors, understanding fellowship criteria, developing project ideas</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Application development (6-12 months):
    <ul>
      <li>Writing, getting feedback, revising multiple times</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Buffer for rejection and resubmission (6-12 months):
    <ul>
      <li>Many successful applicants need 2-3 attempts</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><strong>The two-shot strategy</strong> emerged as particularly valuable advice. Plan your timeline to allow for one rejection and resubmission. This removes pressure from your first application while giving you realistic chances of success.</p>

<h2 id="the-person-place-project-framework">The Person-Place-Project Framework</h2>
<p>Successful applications excel across three dimensions (though different fellowships weigh these differently):</p>

<h3 id="person-your-track-record">Person (Your Track Record)</h3>
<ul>
  <li>Publication quality and independence from supervisors</li>
  <li>Evidence of leadership and collaboration</li>
  <li>Teaching and mentoring experience (for later-career fellowships)</li>
  <li>Professional development and conference presentations</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="place-research-environment">Place (Research Environment)</h3>
<ul>
  <li>Quality and reputation of the host institution</li>
  <li>Mentor’s track record and support</li>
  <li>Available resources and infrastructure</li>
  <li>Research culture and collaboration opportunities</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="project-research-proposal">Project (Research Proposal)</h3>
<ul>
  <li>Scientific significance and innovation</li>
  <li>Feasibility within the proposed timeline</li>
  <li>Clear training and skill development plan</li>
  <li>Appropriate risk level (challenging but achievable)</li>
</ul>

<p>The key insight: <strong>find out what matters most for your target fellowship.</strong> Some prioritize the person, others the project. Tailor your application accordingly.</p>

<h2 id="financial-realities-and-administrative-support">Financial Realities and Administrative Support</h2>

<p><strong>Overhead costs</strong> can make or break applications. Some fellowships cover full overhead, making them attractive to institutions. Others cover minimal research expenses, potentially limiting what research you can actually conduct.</p>

<p>The speakers emphasized: <strong>talk to your grants office early.</strong> They can help navigate complex funding arrangements, matching requirements, and overhead calculations. At Cambridge, some resources can provide matching funds for certain fellowships.</p>

<p><strong>Research expenses</strong> require careful planning. Even substantial fellowships may not cover all your research costs.</p>

<p>Consider:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Whether you can access additional small grants</li>
  <li>If your mentor’s existing grants could support some expenses</li>
  <li>Whether your research design is realistic given the budget</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="the-emotional-journey-rejection-and-persistence">The Emotional Journey: Rejection and Persistence</h2>
<p>Perhaps the most encouraging aspect of the workshop was the candid discussion of rejection. Camilla Nord shared: “I am so good at being rejected from fellowships. I’ve been rejected by every fellowship you can possibly think of in the UK.” Camilla now sits on fellowship panels and has built a successful independent research group.</p>

<p><strong>Rejection is normal and predictable.</strong> Successful researchers typically apply 3-4 times per successful application.</p>

<p><strong>Persistence pays off.</strong> The researchers who have been rejected the most often have also acquired the most funding over their career. Each rejection teaches you something about the process.</p>

<p><strong>Don’t overreact to feedback.</strong> One reviewer’s criticism might not represent broader concerns. Get multiple perspectives before making major changes.</p>

<p><strong>Use rejection strategically.</strong> If you have time for a second application, incorporate feedback thoughtfully. If the feedback seems misguided, you may not need to change much.</p>

<h2 id="work-life-integration">Work-Life Integration</h2>
<p>The panelists also talked about balancing academic careers with personal life, particularly regarding starting a family.</p>

<p>Key insights included:</p>

<p><strong>There’s no perfect time.</strong> Academia’s flexible timeline means you can make most life events work, but it requires planning and communication.</p>

<p><strong>Academia is actually family-friendly.</strong> The flexibility to reschedule meetings, work from home, and adjust hours makes academic careers more compatible with family life than many alternatives.</p>

<p><strong>Plan for maternity/paternity coverage.</strong> Most major funders are generous with parental leave extensions and additional funding.</p>

<h2 id="practical-action-steps">Practical Action Steps</h2>

<p>Based on the workshop insights, here’s what you can do now:</p>

<h3 id="immediate-actions">Immediate Actions</h3>
<ol>
  <li>Assess your independence.
    <ul>
      <li>Do you have publications without your PhD supervisor? If not, start developing collaborations outside your lab.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Research fellowship landscapes.
    <ul>
      <li>Use databases like Research Professional to identify relevant opportunities.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Start networking.
    <ul>
      <li>Contact potential mentors even if applications are years away. Time goes faster than you think.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ol>

<h3 id="medium-term-planning">Medium-term Planning</h3>
<ol>
  <li>Develop project ideas.
    <ul>
      <li>What training do you need? What research questions excite you beyond your thesis?</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Get financial advice.
    <ul>
      <li>Meet with grants offices to understand funding landscapes and requirements.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Build your profile.
    <ul>
      <li>Present at conferences, seek teaching opportunities, develop collaborations.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ol>

<h3 id="long-term-strategy">Long-term Strategy</h3>
<ol>
  <li>Plan your two-shot approach.
    <ul>
      <li>Give yourself time for rejection and resubmission.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Cultivate references.
    <ul>
      <li>The best reference letters come from people who know your work well and can speak to your potential.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Get feedback early and often.
    <ul>
      <li>Share ideas and draft applications widely. Don’t wait until the last minute.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ol>

<h2 id="the-bigger-picture">The Bigger Picture</h2>
<p>Fellowship applications encompass much more than just obtaining funding—they involve cultivating strategic thinking, enhancing resilience, and refining your research vision. Regardless of whether you pursue fellowships or other avenues, taking the time to reflect deeply on your independence, training requirements, and research objectives will benefit you throughout your career.</p>

<p>The most successful researchers are not always the smartest or most talented. Instead, they are individuals who strategically consider their career paths, endure challenges, and foster strong networks among collaborators and mentors.</p>

<p>As Sare de Felice summarized: “There are advantages and disadvantages to every path. The key is making informed choices about what works for your research, your life, and your goals.”</p>

<h2 id="fellowship-spotlight-key-opportunities-mentioned">Fellowship Spotlight: Key Opportunities Mentioned</h2>

<p><strong><a href="https://wellcome.org/research-funding/schemes/wellcome-early-career-awards">Wellcome Early Career Award</a></strong>: £400K over 5 years, highly competitive, excellent training support</p>

<p><strong><a href="https://www.leverhulme.ac.uk/early-career-fellowships">Leverhulme Early Career Fellowship</a></strong>: Requires 50% institutional matching, strong for career development</p>

<p><strong><a href="https://marie-sklodowska-curie-actions.ec.europa.eu/actions/postdoctoral-fellowships">Marie Skłodowska-Curie Postdoctoral Fellowship</a></strong>: EU-wide, excellent for international mobility</p>

<p><strong><a href="https://www.thebritishacademy.ac.uk/funding/postdoctoral-fellowships/">British Academy Postdoctoral Fellowship</a></strong>: For social science framing, includes overhead support</p>

<p>The fellowship landscape is complex and constantly evolving, but the principles shared in this workshop—strategic thinking, persistence, and building independence—are good guidelines for navigating these opportunities.</p>

<p><em>Remember: every successful researcher has a story of rejection and persistence. Your setbacks are not signs of failure—they’re part of the journey toward success.</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Emily Towner</name><email>hello@emilytowner.com</email></author><category term="academia" /><category term="postdoctoral" /><category term="fellowship" /><category term="postdoc" /><category term="grants" /><category term="funding" /><category term="career development" /><category term="independence" /><category term="research strategy" /><category term="cambridge" /><category term="persistence" /><category term="networking" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Postdoctoral fellowships receive a vast number of applications for a very limited number of positions. This sobering reality captures the harsh truth about academic fellowships. However, at the same time, a really good predictor of fellowship success comes down to how many times you’ve applied and how persistent you are.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://emilyedited.com/assets/images/posts/2025/06/04/fellowship-game-insider.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://emilyedited.com/assets/images/posts/2025/06/04/fellowship-game-insider.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Why Your Brain Keeps Chasing That Next Reward: The Science Behind Our Drive for More</title><link href="https://emilyedited.com/emotion/neuroscience/science/psychology/2025/06/03/brain-reward-system.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why Your Brain Keeps Chasing That Next Reward: The Science Behind Our Drive for More" /><published>2025-06-03T11:30:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-06-03T11:30:00+01:00</updated><id>https://emilyedited.com/emotion/neuroscience/science/psychology/2025/06/03/brain-reward-system</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://emilyedited.com/emotion/neuroscience/science/psychology/2025/06/03/brain-reward-system.html"><![CDATA[<p>Ever notice how that dopamine hit from checking your phone feels so good in the moment, but leaves you wanting more just minutes later? Or how you can be completely exhausted but still find yourself scrolling through social media at 2 AM? There’s actually fascinating psychology behind why this happens—and it all comes down to how your brain evolved to keep you alive.</p>

<h2 id="your-brain-the-ultimate-survival-machine">Your Brain: The Ultimate Survival Machine</h2>

<p>Here’s the thing about rewards: they’re not just nice-to-have experiences. They’re absolutely crucial for survival and reproduction. Your brain basically evolved as a sophisticated reward-seeking machine because organisms that were good at finding food, water, safety, and mates were the ones that survived long enough to pass on their genes.</p>

<p>But how does this ancient survival system actually work in your moment-to-moment experience? Your brain uses rewards in three main ways:</p>

<h3 id="learning">Learning</h3>

<p>Rewards teach you what’s important and how to get it. That amazing coffee shop you discovered? Your brain filed that location away as “valuable resource here.”</p>

<h3 id="motivation">Motivation</h3>

<p>Rewards drive you to seek them out and choose between options. When you’re deciding between Netflix and the gym, your brain is weighing which option feels more rewarding right now.</p>

<h3 id="positive-emotions">Positive Emotions</h3>

<p>Rewards create those good feelings that make you want to pursue them again. The satisfaction of completing a challenging workout isn’t just nice—it’s your brain’s way of saying “do this again.”</p>

<h2 id="not-all-rewards-are-created-equal">Not All Rewards Are Created Equal</h2>

<p>Your brain categorizes rewards into different types, and understanding this helps explain why some things are so much harder to resist than others.</p>

<h3 id="primary-rewards">Primary Rewards</h3>

<p>The basics: food, water, sleep, sex. These are hardwired to feel good because they directly support survival. You don’t need to learn that water tastes amazing when you’re thirsty—evolution took care of that programming.</p>

<h3 id="non-primary-rewards">Non-primary Rewards</h3>

<p>These help you get primary rewards indirectly. Money is the classic example. A twenty-dollar bill doesn’t nourish you directly, but it can buy you food, shelter, or other necessities. Your brain learns to value these tools for survival.</p>

<h3 id="intrinsic-rewards">Intrinsic Rewards</h3>

<p>These are activities that feel rewarding just for their own sake—exploring, creating music, solving puzzles, reading a great book. These might seem unrelated to survival, but they actually broaden your skills and knowledge in ways that can pay off later. The musician might use their skills to attract a partner, or the explorer might discover new resources.</p>

<p>Interestingly, research shows that computational models incorporating intrinsic motivation actually outperform systems driven only by external rewards in the long run. This suggests that your brain’s tendency to pursue things “just because they’re interesting” isn’t a bug—it’s a feature that makes you more adaptable.</p>

<h2 id="the-prediction-game-your-brain-plays">The Prediction Game Your Brain Plays</h2>

<p>But here’s where it gets really fascinating: your brain isn’t just reacting to rewards when you get them. It’s constantly trying to predict what’s coming next.</p>

<p>When a stimulus consistently appears before a reward—like your phone buzzing before you see a text message—your brain learns that sound is a reward predictor. Eventually, just hearing that notification sound triggers anticipation and maybe even gets you reaching for your phone.</p>

<p>The key insight here is that simply experiencing things together isn’t enough for strong learning. The reward outcome actually has to depend on the stimulus being there. This is called contingency. If your phone randomly gave you good news whether it buzzed or not, that buzzing sound wouldn’t become such a powerful trigger.</p>

<p>Your brain tracks this through something called prediction error—basically the difference between what you expected and what you actually got. When you get something better than expected, that’s a positive prediction error (surprise and delight!). When you get less than expected, that’s negative (disappointment). When you get exactly what you predicted, there’s no prediction error and no need to update your mental model.</p>

<h2 id="your-brains-teaching-signal">Your Brain’s Teaching Signal</h2>

<p>This is where dopamine comes in—and it’s way more sophisticated than just being a “pleasure chemical.” In the context of learning, dopamine neurons specifically signal prediction error. When you get an unexpectedly good reward, they fire in quick bursts. When a predicted reward fails to arrive, their activity drops below baseline. And crucially, when you get exactly what you expected, there’s no change in their firing.</p>

<p>Dopamine isn’t shouting “yay, reward!”—it’s more like “whoa, that was different than I thought!” This surprise signal is what drives learning and keeps your brain’s reward map updated as you navigate the world.</p>

<h2 id="the-complexity-of-value">The Complexity of Value</h2>

<p>Now here’s where things get really complex: your brain doesn’t just calculate value based on the reward itself. It considers everything—your current internal state, the effort required, how long you have to wait, the risk involved, what you expected based on past experience, and even what’s happening with other people around you.</p>

<p>Think about food. That slice of pizza has completely different subjective value when you’re starving versus when you’ve just finished a huge meal. The same reward, but your brain’s value calculation changes dramatically based on your internal state.</p>

<p>Context matters too. That coffee shop doesn’t just contain coffee—the whole environment has become associated with the good feelings you get there. Your brain literally values the space itself.</p>

<p>And then there’s effort. Your brain clearly calculates effort costs and weighs them against potential payoff. That workout has to feel worth the physical discomfort to be motivating. Interestingly, when you enjoy the activity itself (remember intrinsic rewards?), that intrinsic reward can sometimes outweigh significant effort costs, making hard work feel less burdensome or even pleasurable.</p>

<p>Time also plays a huge role through something called temporal discounting. We almost universally value immediate rewards more than future ones, even when the future reward is objectively better. A reward right now feels better than the same reward next week. This might have evolutionary roots—in an uncertain world, immediate rewards were often safer bets than promises of future payoff.</p>

<h2 id="the-social-element">The Social Element</h2>

<p>Your brain is also incredibly sensitive to social factors when calculating value. How rewards are distributed among people definitely matters to your own subjective experience. Getting less than others feels particularly bad (equity aversion), and often this negative feeling is stronger than the positive feeling from getting more than others.</p>

<p>Your brain literally tracks not just your own rewards, but also rewards going to others around you. It even distinguishes who performed the action to get the reward. Your sense of fairness is deeply embedded in your reward system.</p>

<h2 id="when-biology-constrains-choice">When Biology Constrains Choice</h2>

<p>This brings us to something profound about free will. All of this sophisticated reward machinery that we’ve been discussing—the prediction learning, subjective value calculation, decision variables—this system that’s so crucial for survival also sets fundamental limits on what we experience as free choice.</p>

<p>Your biological need for essential rewards like food, water, and safety isn’t really a domain of free choice in the philosophical sense. You have to pursue them. When you’re severely thirsty and you choose to seek water, that might feel less like a truly free deliberation and more like following a hardwired intention.</p>

<p>Even when you have multiple options, the underlying drive to maximize utility—to get the most value for survival—imposes significant boundaries on what you’ll seriously consider. Think about habits, or more dramatically, addiction. These are conditions where the very reward system that’s supposed to help you make good choices has been altered in ways that drastically reduce the scope of genuine choice.</p>

<h2 id="what-this-means-for-you">What This Means for You</h2>

<p>Understanding how your reward system works doesn’t eliminate its influence, but it can help you work with it more effectively. That compulsive phone checking? Your brain has learned that the notification sound predicts social rewards, and it’s doing exactly what it evolved to do—pursue potentially valuable information.</p>

<p>The key insight is that your brain is actively constructing a rich, dynamic landscape of subjective value using sophisticated learning and decision mechanisms that were tuned by millions of years of evolution. Your daily choices—whether to check social media, what to eat, when to exercise—aren’t just arbitrary decisions. They’re the output of an incredibly complex biological system that’s constantly optimizing for what it perceives as valuable for your survival and wellbeing.</p>

<p>This doesn’t mean you’re helpless. But it does suggest that effective behavior change works with your reward system rather than against it. Instead of relying purely on willpower, you can think about how to restructure your environment to change what your brain predicts and values.</p>

<p>The question isn’t whether this biological reward system influences your behavior—it absolutely does. The question is how understanding it might help you make choices that align with your longer-term goals and values, even when your ancient survival brain is pulling you in a different direction.</p>

<p>After all, awareness of the machine doesn’t make you less human. It just gives you better insight into what it means to be human in the first place.</p>]]></content><author><name>Emily Towner</name><email>hello@emilytowner.com</email></author><category term="emotion" /><category term="neuroscience" /><category term="science" /><category term="psychology" /><category term="dopamine" /><category term="motivation" /><category term="behavior" /><category term="brain" /><category term="reward" /><category term="prediction" /><category term="decision-making" /><category term="evolution" /><category term="survival" /><category term="neurotransmitters" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Ever notice how that dopamine hit from checking your phone feels so good in the moment, but leaves you wanting more just minutes later? Or how you can be completely exhausted but still find yourself scrolling through social media at 2 AM? There’s actually fascinating psychology behind why this happens—and it all comes down to how your brain evolved to keep you alive.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://emilyedited.com/assets/images/posts/2025/06/03/brain-reward-system.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://emilyedited.com/assets/images/posts/2025/06/03/brain-reward-system.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>